Guide to the Nancy Hanks Papers, 1894-1987 (bulk 1945-1983)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nancy Hanks papers 1894-1987 (bulk 1945-1983)
Hanks, Nancy, 1927-1983
77.3 linear feet Extent: 58,000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00504
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are restricted, in particular some of the Friends of the Nancy Hanks Center interviews and questionnaires.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Nancy Hanks (1927-1983), arts organization administrator and consultant, were a series of gifts to the Duke University Library from 1980 to 2000.
Biographical Note
1927, Dec. 31 Born, Miami Beach, Fla.
1945 Graduated, Montclair High School, Montclair, New Jersey
1946, summer Attended the University of Colorado
1948, summer Attended Oxford University
1949 B.A., magna cum laude, Duke University
1951-1952 Secretary to the Director of the Office of Defense Mobilization
1953 President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization
1953-1954 Assistant to the Under Secretary, Department of Health, Education and Welfare
1955-1956, Feb. Assistant to the Special Assistant to the President on Foreign Affairs
1956-1959 Assistant to Nelson A. Rockefeller
1959-1969 Associate, Laurance S. Rockefeller; Executive Secretary, Special Studies Project, Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Project Coordinator, The Performing Arts: Problems and Prospects; and Staff Coordinator, Prospect for America
1969-1977 Chairman, National Endowment for the Arts and National Council on the Arts
1977-1983 Vice Chairman, Rockefeller Brothers Foundation
1983, Jan. 7 Died
Board of Directors: Equitable Life Assurance Society of the U.S., Continental Oil Company (Conoco), Scholastic, and Salzburg Seminar in American Studies
Member: American Council for the Arts (President, 1968-1969), American Association of Museums (Member council, 199), American Society of Landscape Architects, National Commission for Urban Recreation, Indo-U.S. Sucommission on Education and Culture, and White House Conference on Aging
Trustee: Duke University (also on executive committee), Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., and Conservation Foundation
Numerous awards and honorary degrees
Collection Overview
The papers of Nancy Hanks span the years 1894-1987 with the bulk occurring during the 1940s to 1983. Included are correspondence; minutes; reports; typed, mimeographed, and printed material; financial papers; clippings; mail logs; telephone records; calendars; office files; interviews, questionnaires; and diaries. In addition there are scrapbooks, pictures, photograph albums, slides, audio cassettes, videocassettes, and electronic documents. One series contains awards, honorary degrees, and memorabilia.
The Nancy Hanks collection is useful as a study of the development of private and governmental arts programs, in particular through the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), and the personal life and career (1950s-1970s) of an upper-class single woman. Arts and the federal government is a recurrent theme. The collection also contains information about a variety of arts organizations in which Hanks was involved, often as a board member. Although the papers here document both her personal and professional life and present a balanced account, there are relatively few professional papers in the collection concerning her early career, 1951-1968.
The private life of Nancy Hanks is chiefly documented in the Personal Series. Although there are no diaries in the collection, the letters she wrote to her parents from the 1940s through the 1970s form a type of diary. This correspondence in the Personal Series often contains a detailed accounting of daily events from her college years at Duke University, where she majored in political science, and her early career in Washington, D.C., through the NEA years. Letters from her parents reveal their influence on her and often note their advice to her. Other correspondence is from friends, some during World War II, including extensive correspondence from 1946 to 1949 with William A. Carpenter, a former college friend. Other correspondents were Louis E. Reid, 1955-1961; John F. Watkins, 1949-1950; and Duke University Dean of Chapel James T. Cleland, 1949-1969. The financial papers in that series reveal her wealth, such as in real estate and stocks, as well as her long illness. There are gaps in the tax returns and bank statements from 1966-1975 and after 1979.
The Duke University, Bryan and Virginia Hanks, Larry Hanks, and Pictures Series all complete the story. In the Duke University Series, Hanks' financial contributions to the university are documented, including the Hanks Family Endowment Fund and the Hanks Family Chapel Fund.
The Bryan and Virginia Hanks Series and Larry Hanks Series contain records of Hanks' parents, Bryan Cayce Hanks, Virginia Wooding Hanks, and brother Lawrence (Larry) Wooding Hanks. Included in the Bryan and Virginia Hanks Series are late-nineteenth century documents, letters of Hanks' father from France during World War I and from a Colorado sanatarium, 1931-1932, as well as their courtship letters. Bryan Hanks was a lawyer in New York, Miami, and Fort Worth, and became president of Florida Power and Light Company in 1937. Also there is some Hanks and Wooding families history, including a few papers of Benjamin Franklin Wooding, Nancy's maternal grandfather. He was a medical doctor and inventor who developed an automatic train control device and automatic block controls for prevention of railroad accidents. The Larry Hanks Series tells the story of the early death of Nancy Hanks' younger brother, who was killed in a truck accident in California in June, 1950 at the age of eighteen while a student at Southwestern University.
In this collection it is primarily the NEA portion of Hanks' career, 1968-1977 during the Nixon and Ford years, that is represented. However, there is some information in the letters to Hanks' parents in the Personal Series which reflects her early work, 1951-1968. During her tenure at NEA there were vast increases in NEA funding. The NEA was established in 1965 with the National Endowment for the Humanities as components of the National Foundation on the Arts and the Humanities. In the National Endowment for the Arts Series there is a narrative entitled, "Ten Years for Tomorrow," which contains much biographical information about Hanks' NEA years. While at NEA Hanks delivered numerous speeches; in fact from 1971 to 1974 she made about 100 addresses. These years are also documented in the American Film Institute (AFI), Commission on Critical Choices for Americans, and National Council on the Arts series, which depict related responsibilities of Hanks. AFI files document the organization's efforts to preserve the heritage and art of both film and television in America. National Council on the Arts files reflect programs in the areas of architecture, dance, education, expansion arts, literature, museums, music, visual arts, exhibitions, and theater. The Personal Series, Pictures Series, and Awards and Memorabilia Series provide supplemental information. Letters Hanks wrote to her parents as well as other correspondence and notes in the Personal Series relating to the NEA show her continuing interest in the agency after retirement. Related papers for the NEA are housed at the National Archives.
The alphabetical files in the Personal Series document her board work, memberships, and interest in a variety of organizations and institutions, including those related to the arts. They include the Awards in the Visual Arts, Commission on Museums for a new Century, Continental Oil Company (Conoco), the Conservation Foundation, the Equitable Life Assurance Society of the U.S., the Independent Sector, the Indo-U.S. Subcommission on Education and Culture, Partners for Livable Places, the Phillips Collection, Presidential Task Force on the Arts and Humanities, Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, Scholastic, Inc., and Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution. One measure of the public recognition of Hanks' work is the fact that during 1970 to 1981 she received 27 honorary doctoral degrees. The National Endowment for the Arts Series office files, Rockefeller Brothers Fund Series, and the Personal Series alphabetical files all contain single folders for a variety of art, dance, and music organizations.
Papers relating to Nelson Rockefeller are scattered throughout the collection. The Rockefeller Brothers Fund Series contains material relating to Nelson A., John D., 3rd, and Laurance. In the Personal Series is information on Nelson A. Rockefeller and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Hanks' correspondence with her parents also discusses her relationship with Nelson Rockefeller.
There are papers in the collection that reflect both Hanks' retirement years as well as activities of colleagues after her death in 1983. One measure of Hanks' post-NEA involvement is that in 1982 she was on the boards of three corporations and a foundation, as well as being trustee or advisor for 20 non-profit organizations. Related materials are in the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and Friends of the Nancy Hanks Center, Inc. series. The papers of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, where Hanks was a vice chairman, do not appear to provide a complete record of her work there. These files are probably scattered ones that she kept at home and often were not clearly defined.
The U.S. government designated the Old Post Office space on Pennsylvania Avenue as the Nancy Hanks Center. The Friends of the Nancy Hanks Center was formed to initiate programs commemorating Hanks' life and advancing her values. Most of the interviews in this series were conducted by Peter Jessup, but Donna Mitchell conducted a number of them. Many of these interviews exist as electronic files and are available to researchers. These files are listed in the container list for the Friends of the Nancy Hanks Center, Inc. Series.
A related collection in the Duke University Special Collections Department is the Philip Hanes collection. In addition, Hanes material appears in the Hanks Papers in the Personal Series both under his name and in the Awards in the Visual Arts folders.
Subject Headings
Art and state; Art societies; Arts -- Endowments; Arts -- United States; Arts administrators -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Awards in the Visual Arts; Federal Aid to the arts; Independent Sector; Indo-U.S. Subcommission on Education and Culture; Single women; Women government executives -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Women in public life; American Film Institute; Hanks, Nancy, 1927-1983; Biddle, Livingston, 1918-; Booth, John E. (John Erlanger); Cleland, James T.; Commission on Critical Choices for Americans; Commission on Museums for a New Century; Conservation Foundation; Continental Oil Company; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-; Friends of the Nancy Hanks Center (Washington, D.C.); Hanes, R. Philip, 1926-; Hanks family; Hayes, Helen, 1900-; Horowitz, Harold; Irwin, George M.; Kissinger, Henry, 1923-; National Council on the Arts; National Endowment for the Arts; Partners for Livable Places; Pell, Claiborne, 1918-; Phillips Collection; Presidential Task Force on the Arts and Humanities; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Salzburg Seminar in American Studies; Scholastic; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent; Smithsonian Institution. Board of Regents; Stover, Carl Frederick, 1930-; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Wooding family
Contents of Collection
- American Film Institute Series, 1967-1979and undated, (2.5 boxes)
  Minutes, memoranda, letters, reports, contracts, and budgets; much mimeographed material. Papers begin in the year the AFI became a private, non-profit corporation, although still relying on government funds, and run through Hanks' years as National Endowment for the Arts chairman. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Appropriations: Fiscal Years, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Center for Advanced Film Studies, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Conference Report to H.R. 8773, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Congressional Letters, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Establishment, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Film and Television Presentation, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Hearings, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Letters and Testimony, 1970-1972 and undated (Box 2)
  - Meeting Information, 1973 and undated (Box 2)
  - Notes (Nancy Hanks), 1971-1974 and undated (Box 2)
  - Program and Financial Plan, and Education Proposal, Fiscal Years 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Public Media Advisory Panels, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Reorganization, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Revenues, 1975 (Box 3)
- Commission on Critical Choices for Americans Series, 1960-1976(bulk 1973-1976) (5 boxes).
  Chiefly printed material, including draft reports and background papers of six panels. Panel areas of responsibility included energy; food, health, world population, and quality of life; raw materials, industrial development, capital formation, employment, and world trade; international trade and monetary systems; change, national security, and peace; and quality of life of Americans. Arranged alphabetically; folders for panels arranged numerically.
  - Introduction, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
  - Members, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1975 and undated (Box 4)
  - Panel I, 1974-1975, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Panel II, 1974 April, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Panel II, 1974 May-1975 Nov., (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - Panel III, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Panel IV, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Panel V, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Panel VI, 1974 May-July, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Panel VI, 1974 July-1975 June, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Panel VII, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Printed Material 1960-1973 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Third Century Corporation, 1973 (Box 8)
- Duke University Series, 1947-1984(bulk 1970-1982) (3 boxes).
  Correspondence, chiefly letters to Hanks, and subject files, reflecting her board of trustees service at Duke, 1966-1983. Correspondence is filed chronologically, followed by alphabetically-arranged subject files.
  - Correspondence
    - 1947, 1958-1973, (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1974-1982, (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Subject Files
    - Art Museum, 1980-1982 (Box 9)
    - Arts Material (general), 1978-1980 and undated (Box 9)
    - Board and Executive Committee, undated (Box 9)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Center for the Study of Aging, 1978-1982 (Box 9)
    - Commencement Address by Nancy Hanks, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Contributions:
      - Hanks Family Endowment Fund, 1976-1982 and undated (Box 9)
      - Loyalty Fund, 1978-1982 and undated (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970-1982 and undated (Box 10)
      - University Center, 1978-1981 and undated (Box 10)
      - Contributors for Chairs, 1982 and undated (Box 10)
    - Development, 1978-1982 and undated (Box 10)
    - Founders' Society, 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Hanks Family Chapel Fund, 1980-1982 and undated (Box 10)
    - Hanks Family Fund, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 10)
    - Hayes, Helen, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Institute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs (Box 10)
    - Nixon Library, 1981 and undated (Box 10)
    - Papers of Nancy Hanks, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
    - Rockefeller, Laurance S., undated (Box 10)
    - School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 10)
    - School of Nursing, 1978-1981 (Box 10)
    - Student and Campus Affairs, 1977-1982 (Box 10)
    - University Center, 1978-1982 and undated (Box 10)
    - University Medical Center, 1978-1982 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1982 and undated (Box 10)
- National Council on the Arts Series, 1965-1977(20 boxes).
  Notebook contents and folders chiefly while Hanks was chairman of the Council. It is comprised of the chairman of the NEA and 26 other members appointed by the President. Primarily concerns meetings, 1970-1977,but also includes a briefing book for new Council members, memoranda, and letters. Meeting information includes primarily mimeographed minutes, agendas, guidelines for and descriptions of programs, financial information and budgets, resolutions, statements, policy statements, memoranda, and allocations. Two major sections: meetings, and memoranda and letters; each section is filed chronologically.
  - Briefing book for new council members, 1965-1975 (Box 11)
  - Meetings, 1970:
    - Jan.24-26, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - May 22-24, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - May 22-24 (Box 12)
    - Oct. 30-Nov. 1, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Meetings, 1971:
    - Feb. 12-14, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - 13 May 21-23, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - Sept. 10-12, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - 14 Nov. 6-8, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Meetings, 1972:
    - Feb. 18-20, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - May 6-8, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - Aug. 11, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Sept. 22-24, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Nov. 30-Dec. 3, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Meetings, 1973:
    - Feb. 9-11 (Box 16)
    - Feb. 9-11, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - May 11-13, (4 folders) (Box 17)
    - July 29, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Sept. 14-16, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Nov. 30-Dec. 1 (Box 18)
  - Meetings, 1974:
    - Feb. 8-10 (Box 18)
    - Feb. 8-10, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - May 2-4, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - May 2-4, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Sept. 3-5, (4 folders) (Box 20)
    - Nov. 22-24, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Meetings, 1975:
    - Feb. 7-9, (4 folders) (Box 21)
    - May 1-4, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - July 25-27 (Box 22)
    - July 25-27 (Box 23)
    - Sept. 25-27, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - Nov. 21-23, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Nov. 21-23, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Meetings, 1976:
    - Feb. 6-8, (4 folders) (Box 24)
    - May 14-16, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - July, Parts 1 and 2, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Sept., (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - Nov., (2 folders) (Box 26-27)
  - Meetings, 1977:
    - Feb. (4 folders) (Box 27)
    - April (Box 27)
  - Meetings, 1977:
    - April (Box 28)
    - May, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - August, Part 1 (Box 28)
  - Meetings, 1977:
    - Aug. Parts 2-4, (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - Memos, letters, etc., 1970 Sept.-1976 Nov., (5 folders) (Box 29)
  - Memos, letters, etc., 1977 Feb.-Nov., undated, (3 folders) (Box 30)
  - Nominations, 1976 (Box 30)
- National Endowment for the Arts Series, 1965-1982and undated(bulk 1969-1977) (47 boxes)
  The second largest series, it reflects Hanks' career as the second Chairman of the Endowment, 1969-1977. Includes memoranda, chiefly carbon copies of Hanks' out-going letters, mimeographs, typed, and photocopies. Major categories include: administrative services memoranda, budgets, clippings (about Hanks, interviews, and her speeches), correspondence (arranged chronologically), honorary degrees, invitations index (notes whether accepted or declined), legislation, mail log, office files (arranged alphabetically by topic), speeches (arranged chronologically), telephone records (include brief remarks and messages about the topic of the calls and a few memoranda), trips (chiefly correspondence and speeches, arranged chronologically), and post-chairmanship (reflects continued NEA involvement after Hanks' chairmanship tenure expired). Office files, the largest section, include several folders for the Support the Arts Program, a national meeting in 1977,and a draft of Ten Years for Tomorrow, a ten-year history of the NEA. Arranged alphabetically by category, then generally chronologically within.
  - Administrative Services Memoranda
    - 1972-1976 Feb., (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1976 Mar.-Aug., (5 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1976 Sept.-1977 Mar., (5 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1977 Apr.-Dec. undated, (3 folders) (Box 32)
  - Budget
    - 1966-1969, (5 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1970-1971, (8 folders) (Box 34)
    - 1972-1973, (6 folders) (Box 35)
    - 1974-1977, (5 folders) (Box 35)
  - Clippings
    - 1969-1975, (3 folders) (Box 36)
    - 1976-1977 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 37)
  - Correspondence
    - 1969-1972 Sept., (4 folders) (Box 37)
    - 1972 Sept. 8-1973, (5 folders) (Box 38)
    - 1974, Jan.-1975, (5 folders) (Box 39)
    - 1976 Jan.-1977 Mar., (5 folders) (Box 40)
    - 1977 June-Sept. 17, (5 folders) (Box 41)
    - 1977 Sept. 30-Dec. and undated, (2 folders) (Box 42)
    - Congratulatory:
      - 1969, A-K, (4 folders) (Box 42)
      - 1969, L-Z, (5 folders) (Box 43)
      - 1973, A-Z (Box 43)
    - Crank, 1976 (Box 43)
    - Gifts, 1972-1977 (Box 43)
    - White House, 1969-1977, (2 folders) (Box 44)
  - Invitations
    - Declined, 1975-1977 (Box 44)
    - Index. 1970-1977 Nov., (4 folders) (Box 44)
  - Legislation
    - 1965-1971 (Box 44)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 45)
  - Mail log
    - 1975-1977, (3 folders) (Box 45)
  - Office Files
    - American Ballet Theatre, 1976-1977 (Box 45)
    - American Crafts Council, 1976 (Box 45)
    - American Symphony Orchestra League, 1974-1976 (Box 45)
    - American University, 1976 (Box 45)
    - Appalachian Regional Commission, 1976 (Box 45)
    - Appropriations for Fiscal Year 1974-1977, (3 folders) (Box 46)
    - Architecture and Environmental Arts, 1975 (Box 46)
    - Artists-in-Schools, 1976-1977 (Box 46)
    - Artrain, 1977 (Box 46)
    - The Arts Councils and Endowment: Overview for Discussion of Future (Box 46)
    - Directions, 1977 (Box 46)
    - "The Arts in Europe," 1976 (Box 46)
    - Arts/Media Program, 1972 (Box 46)
    - Arts Trend Data Study, 1976 (Box 47)
    - Associated Councils of the Arts, 1969-1971 (Box 47)
    - Audience Development Grants, 1977 (Box 47)
    - Benedict's Survey, 1976 (Box 47)
    - Bicentennial, 1972-1977 and undated (Box 47)
    - Board of Directors Training, 1977 (Box 47)
    - California Arts Legislation, 1975 (Box 47)
    - Carter on the Arts, 1976 (Box 47)
    - CEMREL Project, St. Louis, MO, 1974-1975 (Box 47)
    - CETA, 1973-1977 (Box 47)
    - The Corbet Foundation, 1976 (Box 48)
    - Challenge Grants, 1976-1977 (Box 48)
    - Chairman's Office:
      - Survey, 1974 (Box 48)
      - Closing of, 1977 (Box 48)
    - City Spirit, 1976-1977 (Box 48)
    - Community Arts Agencies, 1976-1977 (Box 48)
    - Congressional Liaison Office, 1975-1977 (Box 48)
    - Congressional Task Force, 1975 (Box 48)
    - Council on Foundations: Goals, 1976-1981 (Box 49)
    - Dance, 1976-1977 (Box 49)
    - Design, 1977 (Box 49)
    - Economic Survey of Arts Organizations, 1977 (Box 49)
    - Education Program, 1976-1977 (Box 49)
    - Emergency Employment Act, 1975-1976 (Box 49)
    - Expansion Arts Grants 1972, 1976-1977 (Box 49)
    - Federal Agencies and the Arts 1972, 1977 (Box 49)
    - Federal-State Partnership, 1977 (Box 49)
    - Fellowships, 1975 (Box 49)
    - Fellowship in Performing Arts Administration, 1976 (Box 50)
    - Financial Management for the Arts, 1976 (Box 50)
    - Fine Arts Commission, 1975-1976 (Box 50)
    - Folk Arts, 1977 (Box 50)
    - Funding (case studies), undated (Box 50)
    - General Educational Activities of the Arts Endowment, Draft, 1976 (Box 50)
    - General Operating Support, 1975 (Box 50)
    - General Services Administration, 1975-1976 (Box 50)
    - Graham, Martha, Gala, 1972-1973, 1976 (Box 50)
    - Grant Processing, 1975, undated (Box 50)
    - Grants from Private Sector, 1975-1976 (Box 50)
    - Grants to New York State and other states, 1975 (Box 50)